快點幹完活！
Finish work!
到棚屋去
Go to hut.
是啊 要不讓新來的俘虜
Yeah, that figures.
看到我們在挖墳墓 他們會要逃跑的
If the new prisoners see us digging graves, they may run.
沒時間說笑了 快點幹！
No time for jokes. Finish work!
挖 挖
Dig, dig.
把我們算作病號 怎麼樣？
How about putting us on sick list?
發發慈悲吧 上尉 把我們放到醫院塈a
Have a heart, captain. Put us in hospital.
你現在沒有病 你從來沒有病
You no sick. You never sick.
你為什麼一直要裝病 捨爾斯？
Why you always play sick, Shears?
我猜我不想放個這玩意兒在我頭頂上
Don't want one of these over my head, I guess.
金松上尉…
Captain Kanematsu...
…煙屁股怎麼樣？
...how about a butt?
我今早才給你的 給你們倆
I give you butt this morning. Both of you.
是的 我不是那意思 我想回報一下
That's what I mean. I want to return the favour.
當一個好心人給我禮物…
When a man gives a gift from the goodness of his heart...
…就像你給我那煙屁股 我會牢記在心的
...like you gave me that butt, I remember it from the heart.
這就是為什麼…
That's why...
…我想給你這打火機
...l want you to keep this lighter.
以為是我偷的？
Think I stole it?
這是我們剛剛埋的那個英國小伙子的
It belonged to that English kid we just buried.
是他感激我而送給我的
He gave it to me for a favour I'd done him.
在我死前 我想把它送給你
Before I pass on, I want to do the same for you.
你這個人真有趣 捨爾斯
You funny man, Shears.
你現在是病號了 他也是
You go on sick list. Him too.
總有一天 Saito 上校會發現你在賄賂他…
One of these days Colonel Saito will catch you bribing him...
…那時我們會怎麼樣？
...then where'll we be?
在那之前 我們早就離開這堣F 夥計
Before that happens we'll be far away from here, chum.
逃得遠遠的
Far away.
好吧 我們收工吧
Okay, let's knock off.
這婼鷁菕K
Here lies....
我忘掉了我們剛才埋的是誰
I forgot who we just buried.
湯姆森
Thomson.
啊 對
Ah, yes.
這婼鷁蛬息B特 湯姆森下士…
Here lies Corporal Herbert Thomson...
…編號是:01234567
...serial number zero- one- two-  three- four- five- six- seven.
國王或女王或著什麼的勇敢的戰士…
Valiant member of the King's Own or the Queen's Own or something...
…在我主紀元1943 死於腳氣病…
...who died of beri- beri in the year of our Lord, 1 943...
…為了光榮偉大的…
...for the greater glory of....
- 他是為了什麼死的？ - 算了
- What did he die for? - Come off it.
不要嘲笑死人
No need to mock the grave.
我沒有嘲笑死人
I don't mock the grave or the man.
希望他能在和平中安息
May he rest in peace.
雖然在他活著的時候沒有找到和平
He found little of it while he was alive.
A 隊 原地踏步走！
"A" Company, mark time!
原地踏步走！
Mark time!
立定
Halt.
排成一行 向左轉
Into line, left turn.
稍息
Stand easy.
我們又要挖很多墓 維佛
We're going to be busy gravediggers, Weaver.
幹的好 幹的好
Well done, well done.
那個上校還不知道他將會遭遇到什麼
That colonel doesn't know what he's in for.
你準備去告訴他真相？
You going to tell him the truth?
當然不
Of course not.
你既不是軍官也不是個紳士
You're neither an officer nor a gentleman.
我叫 尼科爾森
My name is Nicholson.
我是Saito 上校
I am Colonel Saito.
我以天皇的名義…
In the name of His lmperial Majesty...
…歡迎你們
...l welcome you.
我是這個戰俘營的指揮官…
I am the commanding officer of this camp...
…這堿O沿著這條大鐵路…
...which is Camp 1 6...
…的第16戰俘營…
...along the great railroad...
…這條鐵路很快就將曼谷和仰光連接起來
...which will soon connect Bangkok with Rangoon.
你們這些英軍俘虜…
You British prisoners have been chosen...
…將要去修建一座跨越桂河的大橋
...to build a bridge across the River Kwai.
這將是一個愉快的工作 但需要技能
It will be pleasant work, requiring skill.
軍官也要和士兵一起工作
And officers will work as well as men.
我們小日本軍隊不會養吃白飯的懶人
The Japanese Army cannot have idle mouths to feed.
如果你努力工作 就會得到優待
If you work hard, you will be treated well.
但是如果你不努力工作…
But if you do not work hard...
…你將受到懲罰
...you will be punished.
關於逃跑 我要說幾句
A word to you about escape.
這堥S有鐵絲網
There is no barbed wire.
沒有圍欄
No stockade.
也沒有瞭望哨
No watchtower.
這些都不需要
They are not necessary.
我們處於熱帶雨林中一個孤島
We are an island in the jungle.
逃出去是不可能的
Escape is impossible.
會死在雨林中的
You would die.
今天休息 明天開始幹活
Today you rest. Tomorrow you'll begin.
最後讓我告訴你們山下將軍的格言:
Let me remind you of General Yamashita's motto:
"在工作中尋求快樂"
" Be happy in your work."
在工作中尋求快樂
Be happy in your work.
解散
Dismissed.
全體 稍息
Battalion, stand at ease.
出隊 休斯上校
Fall out, Major Hughes.
全體 稍息
Battalion, stand easy.
休斯 把他們帶到崗位上去 看看誰生病了
Hughes, get the men to their quarters. See who's sick.
我要和這傢伙說句話
I'm going to have a word with this fellow.
我剛才聽了你的訓話 先生
I heard your remarks just now, sir.
我的部下會堅持英國士兵的一貫方式
My men will carry on in the way one expects of a British soldier.
我的軍官和我會對他們的行為負責
My officers and I will be responsible for their conduct.
你可能沒注意到讓軍官去勞動…
You may have overlooked the fact that the use of officers for labour...
…在日內瓦公約中是不允許的
...is expressly forbidden by the Geneva Convention.
是那樣的嗎？
Is that so?
我有一份公約的複印件…
I have a copy of the convention...
…我很樂意讓你看一下
...and would be glad to let you glance through it.
不用了
That will not be necessary.
請坐
Sit down, please.
是 長官
Yes, sir.
我要和科林普頓說句話
I'm going to have a word with Clipton.
科林普頓 不要讓別人打擾我
Clipton, don't let me interrupt.
- 胳膊怎麼樣了？ - 快好了
- How's the arm? - Nearly healed.
先生 這是美國海軍的捨爾斯司令官
Sir, this is Commander Shears of the United States Navy.
你好 先生
How do you do, sir?
我們發現他和一個澳大利亞人
We found him and an Australian.
是修建這個營地的僅存俘虜
All that's left of the prisoners who built the camp.
美國海軍？ 大老遠的跑到這堙H
U.S. Navy? Out here?
我們差不多被陸地包圍了
I am sort of landlocked.
- 然後你丟棄了你的船？ - 休斯頓號
- You lost your ship? - The Houston.
我讓它擱淺 但是我和其他的倖存者失散了
I made it ashore, but I got separated from the other survivors.
這兒原來和你在一起的人呢？
And your group here?
多數是澳洲人 一些…
Mostly Aussies. Some lime...
英國人還有印度人 緬甸人 暹羅人
Some British. Indians, Burmese, Siamese.
他們怎麼了？
And what happened to them?
他們都死於…
They died...
…瘧疾 痢疾 腳氣和壞疽
...of malaria, dysentery, beri- beri, gangrene.
其他的死因是:
Other causes of death:
飢餓 勞累過度 槍傷 蛇咬…
Famine, overwork, bullet wounds, snakebites...
…還有 Saito
...Saito.
然後還有一些不想過了
Then there were some who just got tired of living.
科林普頓給你檢查過了嗎？
Has Clipton seen you?
正好就要看了 過來 你可以待會刮臉
Just about to. Come over here, you can shave later.
好的
All right.
你可以和軍官待在一起
You'll stay with the officers.
我們會給你找一些像樣的衣服
We'll find some decent clothing.
不要為我操心了
Don't bother about me.
我還不想急著離開病號房
I'm not anxious to get off the sick list.
另外 這是勞動工具 這兒流行這個
Besides, this is working kit. It's the fashion here.
你們當時連軍官都干體力勞動嗎？
The officers in your party did manual labour?
我想是的
I think you could call it that.
我可以列舉出那個上校讓我們做的每一點 他叫什麼來著
I raised that very point with Colonel what's- his- name.
齋藤
Saito.
- 我認為他現在明白那樣做是不對的了 - 是嗎？
- I think he understands now. - Is that so?
是的 我必須說明 他看起來好像是那種很通情達理的類型
Yes. I must say he seems quite a reasonable type.
是這樣啊 那我可得抓緊了
Well, I must be pushing on.
7點鐘有個軍官會議
There's an officer's meeting at 7.
- 把你的要求列個單子 - 是 長官
- Give me a list of your requirements. - Yes, sir.
我們會盡量滿足
Anything we can do.
謝謝 長官
Thank you, sir.
- 這是為什麼？ - 別介意
- What is it? - Never mind.
說說看
Go on, say it.
我可以想像出很多稱呼Saito的詞
I can think of a lot of things to call Saito...
…"通情達理" 倒是第一次聽說
...but reasonable, that's a new one.
或許尼科爾森上校對這個詞有不同的定義
Perhaps Col. Nicholson defines the word differently.
有其他補充的嗎？
Any other points?
- 可以允許我說嗎 長官？ - 詹寧斯？
- By your leave, sir? - Jennings?
有關逃跑委員會 我已經和捨爾斯司令官討論過了…
About the escape committee. I've spoken with Cmd. Shears...
不會再有什麼逃跑委員會了
There won't be any escape committee.
我不明白 長官 詹寧斯少尉有個計劃
I don't understand, sir. Lt. Jennings has a plan.
是的 是的 我相信詹寧斯有個計劃 但是 逃到哪堙H
Yes, yes, I'm sure Jennings has a plan, but escape?
逃進雨林？ 那個Saito傢伙說的是對的
Where? lnto this jungle? That fellow, Saito, is right.
這堿O不需要鐵絲網 逃進雨林只有1/100的生存可能
No need for barbed wire here. One chance in 1 00 of survival.
我認為象捨爾斯司令官 那樣有經驗的人會支持我的計劃
I'm sure a man of Cmdr. Shears' experience will back me up on that.
我說過了逃跑成功的可能性是1/100
I'd say that the odds against a successful escape are 1 00 to one.
我可以插個嘴嗎？
But may I add another word?
請
Please.
在這個戰俘營的生存概率還要小
The odds against survival in this camp are even worse.
你已經看到了那些墳墓 他們是你在這堨穻s的真實幾率
You've seen the graveyard. They're your real odds.
放棄逃走的希望…
To give up hope of escape...
…甚至不去考慮逃走 意味著接受死亡宣判
...to stop thinking about it means accepting a death sentence.
為什麼到目前你還沒有試著逃跑呢 司令官先生？
Why haven't you tried to escape, commander?
我在等候良機 等待正確的時間 和正確的夥伴
I'm biding my time. Waiting for the right moment, the right company.
我知道你的感受
I understand how you feel.
當然 作為一個被俘士兵 逃跑是他的天職
Of course, it's the duty of a captured soldier to attempt escape.
但是我和我的部下正處在一個奇怪的境地…
But my men and I are involved in a curious legal point...
而你並不知道這個
...of which you are unaware.
在新加坡 是指揮部命令我們投降的
In Singapore we were ordered to surrender by command headquarters.
請注意 是命令
Ordered, mind you.
所以 在我們這種情況下 逃跑就會違反戰爭法
Therefore, in our case, escape might well be an infraction of military law.
這真有意思 長官
Interesting point, sir.
對不起 長官 我不能同意你的觀點
I'm sorry, sir, I didn't quite follow you.
你想不惜一切代價去遵守法律條文？
You intend to uphold the letter of the law, no matter what it costs?
沒有了法律 指揮官先生 就不會有文明的存在
Without law, commander, there is no civilization.
這正是我的觀點 在這 沒有文明
That's just my point. Here, there is no civilization.
那麼 我們正好有機會在這堣瑗i文明
Then we have the opportunity to introduce it.
我建議否決逃跑的議題
I suggest we drop the subject of escape.
還有什麼要說的嗎？
Is there anything else?
我想我們都清楚了
I think we're clear on the program.
我想從明天開始所有的事情都能順利展開
I want everything to go off smoothly starting tomorrow morning.
並且 請各位記住:
And remember this:
必須要讓我們的人感覺是我們在指揮他們…
Our men must always feel they are still commanded by us...
…而不是小日本
...and not by the Japanese.
這樣 他們就會還是士兵 而不是奴隸
So long as they have that idea, they'll be soldiers and not slaves.
同意我的觀點嗎 指揮官先生？
Are you with me there, commander?
我希望他們還能是士兵 上校
I hope they can remain soldiers, colonel.
可我只是個奴隸
As for me, I'm just a slave.
一個還活著的奴隸
A living slave.
即使在美國人來說 他也是個古怪的傢伙…
Queer bird. Even for an Ameri...
被囚禁得太久了 可憐的傢伙
He's been in isolation too long, poor chap.
這就是脫離自己人的結果 對我們也是個教訓
Cut off from his unit. It should be a lesson to all of us.
英軍俘虜們！
English prisoners!
請注意我不是說"英軍士兵"
Notice I do not say English soldiers.
當你們投降的那一刻起 你們就不是士兵了
From the moment you surrendered, you ceased to be soldiers.
你們要在五月12號前完成大橋
You will finish the bridge by the twelfth day of May.
你們會在小日本工程師的指導下工作
You will work under the direction of a Japanese engineer.
時間很短 所有人都得工作
Time is short. All men will work.
你們的軍官會和你們一起工作
Your officers will work beside you.
投降就是你們的軍官對你們的背叛
This is only just...
這就是對他們背叛你們的處罰
...for it is they who betrayed you by surrender.
羞辱你們就是要讓羞辱他們
Your shame is their dishonour.
是他們告訴你們…
It is they who told you...
…好死不如賴活著
...better to live like a coolie then die like a hero.
是他們讓你們來這堛 不是我
It is they who brought you here, not l.
所以 他們也要和你們一起干體力活
Therefore, they will join you in useful labour.
完畢
That is all.
軍官俘虜們 拿好你們的工具
Officer prisoners, collect your tools.
布拉德利 歸隊
Bradley, back in your place.
我必須讓你注意 Saito上校…
I must call your attention, Colonel Saito...
…在日內瓦公約的27條
...to Article 27 of the Geneva Convention.
" 交戰國可以僱用戰俘去做他們合適做的工作…
" Belligerents may employ prisoners of war...
…指揮官除外… "
...who are fit, other than officers..."
把書給我
Give me the book.
當然你能讀懂英文嗎？我有點懷疑
By all means. You read English, I take it?
- 你能讀懂日文嗎？ - 很遺憾 不會
- Do you read Japanese? - I'm sorry, no.
如果需要翻譯 我想我可以安排
If it's a matter of translation, I'm sure it can be arranged.
你看 規則(Code)指出…
You see, the Code states that...
站著別動
Stand fast in the ranks.
你和我說"規則"？
You speak to me of Code?
你說的是什麼"規則"？
What " Code"?
你說的是懦夫的"規則"！
The coward's code!
你知道什麼是士兵的規則？
What do you know of the soldier's code?
你知道什麼是武士道的規則？ 你什麼都不知道！
Of bushido? Nothing!
你不配當指揮官！
You are unworthy of command!
如果你拒絕遵守文明世界的法規…
If you refuse to abide by the laws of the civilized world...
…那我們要考慮是否有義務去聽從你的命令
...we must consider ourselves absolved from our duty to obey you.
我的軍官不會去做體力勞動
My officers will not do manual labour.
我們走著瞧
We shall see.
所有戰俘開始去工作
All enlisted prisoners to work.
軍士長！ 帶他們去工作
Sergeant Major! Take the men to work.
全體注意 拿起工具
Battalion, take up tools.
向左靠齊 向左轉！
Move to the left in columnar route. Left turn!
"A" 隊 齊步走
"A" Company, by the right, quick march.
向右看
Eyes right.
向前看
Eyes front.
齊步走 向右看
Quick march, eyes right.
" C" 隊
" C" Company, by the right.
他在等什麼？
What's he up to?
好像他不想有人看到
Looks like he doesn't want any witnesses.
現在 你是否會明白一些
Now, you will be reasonable.
命令你的指揮官去開始工作
You will order your officers to work.
不
No.
我數三下
I will count three.
如果數到第三下…
If by the third count...
…你和你的指揮官還沒有去工作的話…
...you and your officers are not on the way to work...
…我就下令開槍
...l will give the order to fire.
他會這樣做的
He's going to do it.
相信我 他確實想殺了他們
Believe me, he's really going to do it.
一
One.
我警告你 上校…
I warn you, Colonel....
二
Two.
等一等！
Stop!
Saito上校 我耳聞目睹了一切
Colonel Saito, I've seen and heard everything.
醫院堛漱H也這樣
So has every man in the hospital.
有太多的證人
They're too many witnesses.
你不能謊稱這是集體逃跑 那些人很多連路都不能走
You can't call it a mass escape. Most of those men can't walk.
這就是你的士兵規則？ 屠殺手無寸鐵的人？
Is this your soldier's code? Murdering unarmed men?
詹寧斯 你看 當個病號多好
You see, Jennings, there are advantages to being on the sick list.
我認為那老傢伙勇氣十足
I'll say this for the old man. He's got guts.
這樣會死得更快
" Into the valley of death rode the 600."
怎麼會那樣 長官？
How's that, sir?
那種愚蠢的勇氣
That kind of guts.
就像他們在1914一樣…
Also the kind they had in 1 91 4...
…那時 軍官們用枴杖來反抗
...when officers fought with only a swagger stick.
- 我明白你的意思 - 你一點也不明白我的意思
- I see what you mean. - You don't see what I mean at all.
那種勇氣會讓我們全部送命的
The kind of guts that can get us all killed.
對不起 長官 我也要和你一起逃跑
Excuse me, sir, I'd like to go along too.
我的胳膊差不多好了 長官 情況確實像你說的那樣
Arm's almost healed, sir, really it is.
那他會同意嗎？
What about him?
他並沒有命令我們不准逃跑 他只是建議我們不逃跑
He didn't order us not to escape, he suggested.
聽著 像你們上校那樣人的建議就是命令
Listen, when a man like your colonel suggests something, it's an order.
又開始了
Here we go again.
Saito上校命令所有軍官去懲戒室
Colonel Saito says all officers to punishment hut.
告訴他們去懲戒室
Tell them to go.
你留下
Not you.
過來
Come.
放了他！
Leave him alone!
他們要把他關進悶室
They're going to put him in the oven.
# For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow
# For he's a jolly good fellow
# And so say all of us
# And so say all of us And so say all of us
# For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow
# For he's a jolly good fellow
# And so say all of us
倒啦！
Timber!
一 二 三 四
One, two, three, four.
不行！
No, no, no!
鬆開！
Let go!
你想來見我？
You wish to see me?
3天來 我一直想見你
I've tried to see you for three days.
上校已經被關在悶室堙K
It's about the colonel. He's been shut up in that hut...
我應該槍斃你
I could have you shot.
那些想逃跑的俘虜是你的手下
Those prisoners who tried to escape, they were in your charge.
對逃跑我毫不知情
I knew nothing about the escape.
那無關緊要
It does not matter.
那些逃跑的人值得尊敬
One must respect those who tried.
在逃亡和死亡的一瞬間…
For a brief moment, between escape and death...
他們又成了戰士
...they were soldiers again.
但是試圖從這堸k出去是愚蠢的
But it is insane to try and escape.
兩個被槍打死 第三個被淹死
Two soldiers shot and the third drowned.
到頭來又有什麼好結果呢？
To what end?
只不過是逃避現實罷了
It was an escape from reality.
這是你的現實
There is your reality.
按計劃 你們今天中午應該修到這堣F
This shows the position work should have reached by noon today.
而實際上只到這
And this shows the position of actual progress.
由於你們上校的愚頑不化 我們的進度遠遠落後了
Because of your colonel's stubbornness, we are far behind schedule.
還不止這些
That is not all.
戰俘還蓄意破壞
Enlisted prisoners sabotaged the work.
是的 我看到的 我早就應該槍斃他們
Yes, I have seen it. I could have them all shot.
然後 誰替你造橋呢？
Then who would build your bridge?
另外 你認為那真的是蓄意破壞嗎？
Besides, are you sure it's sabotage?
沒有了自己的指揮官 他們的工作肯定不會做得太好
The men don't work well without their own officers.
我的指揮官會直接領導他們工作 你們的指揮官要和他們一塊工作
My officers will direct them. Your officers will work beside them.
那要由尼科爾森來決定
That's for Nicholson to decide.
而且就像他說的那樣 這樣做是違背條約的
As he said, it's against the rules.
別和我談什麼條約
Do not speak to me of rules.
這是戰爭！
This is war!
並不是什麼公平的遊戲
This is not a game of cricket.
你的上校是個瘋子
He's mad, your colonel...
完全是瘋了
...quite mad.
請坐
Sit down, please.
我決定了 只讓你一個人去看你們的上校
I have decided to allow you one visit to your colonel.
謝謝
Thank you.
告訴他 如果他的指揮官還不參加勞動的話…
Tell him that if his officers will not work...
我將不得不關閉醫院…
...l'll be forced to close the hospital...
然後你的病人將替他們勞動
...and your patients will work in their place.
會死掉一些人 這全都要怪他
Many will die, and he will be responsible.
去和他講你只有5分鐘時間
Go and speak to him. You have five minutes.
醫生要去看那老夥計了
Doc's going to see the old man.
長官…
Sir....
是科林普頓 長官
It's Clipton, sir.
我給你帶來些東西
I brought you a few things.
- 我的部下怎麼樣了？ - 他們還好 長官
- How are the men? - Fine, sir, fine.
我們給您湊了點肉和一個椰子
We scraped together a little meat and a coconut.
軍官們怎麼樣？
And the officers?
不太好 他們還在關禁閉
Not so good. They're still in detention.
詹寧斯上尉死了
And Lieutenant Jennings.... Jennings is dead.
- 什麼？ - 在逃跑的時候被槍打死了
- What? - Killed, attempting to escape.
還有維佛下士和那個美國人
Also two others, Corporal Weaver and the American.
詹寧斯 真可憐 勇敢的小伙子
Jennings. Poor, brave lad.
我警告過他 對不對？
I warned him, didn't l, Clipton?
長官 我們時間不多了
Look, sir, we haven't much time.
我一邊給你清理 一邊說
I'm going to clean you up a little while I talk.
我有些事情要告訴你
I've got something to tell you.
我和Saito吵過了
I've just had a word with Saito.
那個傢伙是我遇過的最差的指揮官
That man is the worst commanding officer I've ever come across.
他是個瘋子 你說
Actually, I think he's mad. Carry on.
訛詐！
Blackmail!
我知道 長官 但他是認真的
I know, sir, but he means it. I'm sure he does.
很簡單 這是個關於面子的問題 但他是不會屈服的
It's a question of face, pure and simple. And he can't give in.
但那仍然是訛詐
It's still blackmail.
長官 你是撐不過他的
Sir, you can't stand much more of this.
我們那些軍官被憋在那個悶室堣]不是辦法
Wouldn't the officers be better off working than suffocating in that hole?
我們的士兵在盡量地拖延工期
The men are doing a wonderful job. They're going as slow as they dare.
但是Saito在削減他們的食物配額…
But Saito's cut their food rations...
並且一旦他讓病人去工作…
...and if he makes the sick men work....
很顯然就會死很多人
Well, they're going to die. That's all there is to it.
是的 科林普頓 我很清楚
Yes, Clipton, I understand. Truly.
但是你看到了嗎？這關乎原則
But don't you see? It's a matter of principle.
如果我們現在屈服了 就會無休無止 不行
If we give in now, there'll be no end to it. No.
長官 我們陷在雨林 遠離文明
Sir, we're lost in the jungle, a thousand miles from anywhere.
我們是在一個為了達到自己目的可以不擇手段的傢伙的統治下 更別說原則了！
We're under a man who'll stop at nothing to get his way. Principle!
沒有人會知道這兒發生了什麼 也不會有人關心
No one will ever know or care what happens to us.
退一步吧 長官 求求你了！
Give in, sir. Please!
我不會動搖的
I'm adamant.
我不會讓我的軍官去象一個小工一樣干苦力
I will not have an officer from my battalion working as a coolie.
- 時間到 - 好的
- Time. - All right.
謝謝關心我的人
Please thank those concerned.
醫院堛漕C個人都獻了一片肉
Everybody in the hospital contributed one piece.
雷諾茲偷了個椰子
Reynolds stole the coconut.
我們還會給你帶來食物的
We'll be able to get you food sometimes.
我們已經賄賂了一個看管你的守衛
We've bribed one of your guards.
再見 長官 祝好運
Goodbye, sir. And good luck.
多謝
Many thanks.
你說那個美國人被打死了？
Did you say that American was killed?
是的 長官 被槍打倒後淹死了
Yes, sir. Shot and drowned.
計劃逃跑真是個愚蠢的念頭
It's insane to plan escapes.
3人被殺 結果怎麼樣呢？
Three men killed, and to what end?
時間到！
Time!
我們在這堣@定能勝利
Here is where we must win through.
醫生看著我們並搖搖頭 什麼意思
Doc just looked at us and shook his head. Whatever that means.
只有一個意思 上校不會屈服
Means only one thing, the colonel won't give in.
怎麼樣？
Well?
是這樣的
It's like this.
尼科爾森上校不準備向武力屈服
Colonel Nicholson won't give in to force.
這是個原則的問題
It's a question of principle.
作為醫療官 我抗議對他的折磨
As medical officer, I protest the way he's being treated.
他還能活著 真是奇跡
It's a wonder he's still alive.
如果發生悲劇 那和謀殺是一樣的
Should a tragedy occur, it would be tantamount to murder.
要怪就怪他
He is responsible.
不是我
Not l.
你病了？
You sick?
他們都瘋了嗎？
Are they both mad?
或者我也要發瘋了？
Or am I going mad?
太陽也瘋了？
Or is it the sun?
立正！
Attention!
全體立正
Battalion, attention.
英軍俘虜們
English prisoners.
讓我們問一個問題…
Let us ask the question...
…為什麼大橋進展遲緩？
...why does the bridge not progress?
你們知道為什麼 因為你們的指揮官是懶惰的！
You know why, because your officers are lazy!
他們認為自己高人一等 而不願和你們分擔
They think themselves too good to share your burden.
這是不公平的
This is not just.
所以 你們工作起來也不愉快
Therefore, you are not happy in your work.
所以 大橋也沒有什麼進展
Therefore, the bridge does not progress.
但是還有一個原因
But there is another cause.
我不避諱事實
I do not hide the truth.
我很慚愧…
With deep shame and regret...
…我承認也是由於我們的一個小日本狗屎
...l admit to you the failure...
…的無能
...of a member of the Japanese staff.
我是指 Miura上尉
I refer to Lieutenant Miura.
他是一個很差的工程師
He is a bad engineer.
他的指揮毫不稱職
He is unworthy of command.
所以 我把他撤換了
Therefore, I have removed him from his post.
明天 我們重新開始
Tomorrow we begin again.
我會親自指揮
I shall be in personal command.
今天 我們休息
Today we rest.
只有工作而沒有娛樂會很不爽的！
All work and no play make Jack a dull boy!
為了你們明天努力工作…
As token of regard for your efforts in the future...
…我給你們每個人一份禮物
...l give presents to you all.
工作愉快
Let us be happy in our work.
解散
Company, dismissed.
全體解散
Battalion, dismissed.
嘿 看看
Hey, take a look at this.
紅十字！ 他把我們的…
Red Cross! He's given us our...
嘿 他把我方的紅十字包裹發給我們
Hey, he's given us our own Red Cross parcels.
"明天重新開始"
"Tomorrow we begin again."
嘿 哈里 看！
Hey, Harry, look!
他們要把老夥計放出來了
They're letting the old man out.
看來 他們要再毒打他一頓
Most likely going to give him another pasting.
晚上好 上校
Good evening, colonel.
願意過來坐一坐嗎？
Do you mind sitting over here?
我晚飯還沒有吃
I am having rather a late supper.
英國咸牛肉
English corned beef.
不用 謝謝
No, thank you.
產自蘇格蘭
Produce of Scotland.
我寧願它是日本米酒
I prefer it to sake.
我在倫敦呆了3年
I spent three years in London, you know.
我在倫敦工藝學校學習
I studied at the London Polytechnic.
敬你！
Cheers!
抱歉
Sorry.
下次？
Later, perhaps?
也許
Perhaps.
我不是一個好的藝術家
I was not a good artist.
我爸爸不贊成我搞藝術
My father disapproved.
他覺得我應該在軍隊發展
He felt I belonged in the army.
所以我放棄了藝術 改學工程
So I changed from art to engineering.
我必須告訴你 Saito上校
I must tell you, Colonel Saito.
我要將你的行為寫一份完整的報告
I intend to make a full report of your activities.
我不認為你理解我的處境
I do not think you quite realize my position.
- 我必須執行給我的命令 - 噢 當然
- I must carry out my orders. - Oh, quite, quite.
我必須在5月12號之前完成大橋
My orders are to complete the bridge by the 1 2th day of May.
- 我只有12個星期多一點 - 是的
- I have only 1 2 weeks more. - No doubt.
所以 我必須啟用我手上的任何一個人
Therefore, I am compelled to use all available personnel.
軍官不行 除非是管理工作
No officers, except for administration.
但是在這條鐵路線上 所有的軍官都在工作
But officers are working along the entire railway.
你清楚 我也清楚
You know it. I know it.
其他地方的軍官我不管
I'm not responsible for other officers.
從我個人來講 我很震驚
Personally, I'm appalled.
別激動
Let's not get excited.
來枝雪茄嗎？
Will you have a cigar?
不 謝謝
No. Thank you.
當我說所有的指揮官都要勞動的時候…
When I said all officers must work...
…事實上是指少尉至上校階級之各指揮官 並沒有包括你
...naturally, I never meant you, the commanding officer.
我的命令只適用於下級軍官…
My orders were only intended for officers below...
任何軍官都不能做苦力勞動
No officers will do manual labour.
拜託！ 我是要說:
Please! I was about to say:
我通盤考慮過了
I've thought the matter over and have decided...
…我要讓他們大部分做管理工作
...to put majors and above on administrative duties...
…只有很低級的軍官去勞動
...leaving only junior officers to work.
不行 公約關於這個的規定很清楚
No. The Convention's quite clear on that point.
你知道如果大橋不能準時建成 我會怎樣？
Do you know what will happen to me if the bridge is not ready in time?
一點也不知道
I haven't the foggiest.
我必須自殺
I'd have to kill myself.
如果你是我 你會怎樣？
What would you do if you were me?
如果我是你…
I suppose if I were you...
…我想我會自殺
...l'd have to kill myself.
敬你
Cheers.
我警告你 上校…
I warn you, colonel...
…在我死之前 其他的人都得死
...if I am to die, others will die before me.
你明白了嗎？
Do you understand?
科林普頓並沒有這麼說
Clipton did mention that.
但那樣也不能解決你的問題
That won't solve your problem.
我想我們可以達成一個解決辦法
I'm sure we can arrive at a solution.
請坐
Please sit down.
請你告訴我 上校…
Now. Tell me, colonel...
你認為軍人的天職是服從命令嗎？
...do you agree that the first job of an officer is command?
- 當然 - 好的
- Of course. - Good.
現在
Now.
我們來看看你的大橋
Take this bridge of yours.
真是一個巨大的工程
It's quite an enormous undertaking.
坦率地說 我懷疑你的那個叫什麼來著的上尉…
Frankly, I doubt whether your Lieutenant what's- his- name...
三浦
Miura.
能勝任這樣的工作
...is capable of tackling a job of such importance.
另外 我有些軍官 比如堣狻M休斯…
On the other hand, I have officers, Reeves and Hughes for instance...
…他們在印度到處修橋
...who have built bridges all over lndia.
人們都尊敬他們
The men respect them.
尊重對一個軍官來說是很重要的
It's essential for an officer to have that respect.
如果沒有尊重 則不能服眾
If it's gone, he ceases to command.
然後會怎麼樣？ 部下漫無紀律 指揮混亂
What then? Demoralization and chaos.
如果讓這種情況發生 那麼我就是個非常不稱職的指揮官
A poor commander I would be if I allowed that to happen.
也許你忘記了 修建大橋是由我來指揮的
Perhaps you are not aware that the bridge is now under my command.
真的嗎？ 你對進度滿意嗎？
Really? And may I ask, are you satisfied with the work?
- 很不滿意！ - 你證明了我的觀點
- I am not! - You've proved my point.
我痛恨英國人！
I hate the British!
你們被打敗了 還不知羞恥
You are defeated but you have no shame.
你們很頑固 但沒有什麼值得自豪的
You are stubborn but have no pride.
你們會忍耐 但你們沒有勇氣
You endure but you have no courage.
我痛恨英國人！
I hate the British!
這樣不能解決任何問題
Pointless, going on like this.
站著！
Stay there!
暫停！
Stand down. Stand down!
全體立正！
Battalion, attention!
全體 稍息
Battalion, stand at ease.
請…
Please....
你知道今天是什麼日子嗎 上校？
Do you know what is the date today, colonel?
我已經不會記數了
I've lost count.
這是我們1905年
It's the anniversary of our great victory...
大勝俄國人的紀念日…
...over Russia in 1 905.
整個東亞都在慶祝這個日子
Throughout East Asia we are celebrating this date.
趁著這個偉大的日子…
In honour of this occasion...
…我給你的部下放了一天假
...l have given your troops a day of rest.
多謝
Many thanks.
我要宣佈一個特赦
I am declaring a general amnesty.
你和你的軍官可以回到你們的住處
You and your officers may return to your quarters.
作為這個特赦的一部分…
As part of this amnesty...
…軍官不需要做體力勞動了
...it will not be necessary for officers to do manual labour.
他做到了！
He's done it!
應該給某些人發勳章
Somebody deserves a medal, sir.
你的手下有多少人？
How many men in your party?
我不是很清楚 長官
I don't really know, sir.
- 你不清楚？ - 通常有12個人
- You don't know? - Twelve, usually.
今早有一個生病了 長官
One of the men took sick this morning, sir.
有三四個人把他抬到醫院去了
It took three or four to help him to the hospital.
嗯 他病得很厲害 長官
And... He took terrible sick, sir.
一個下士必須清楚他管轄多少人
A corporal should know how many men he has under him.
是 長官
Oh, yes, sir.
你的面部神經有問題嗎？ 否則 不要那樣做鬼臉
Have you a nervous affliction? Stop making those faces.
也許你認為很有趣 但不要那樣做鬼臉
It may be funny to you, but it's not military behaviour.
沒有問題 長官
No, sir.
我們必須停止這些作假行為
We must put a stop to these demonstrations.
- 我說 堣牷H - 什麼 長官？
- I say, Reeves? - Yes, sir?
以前在這類河上修建過大橋嗎？
Ever built a bridge over a stream like the Kwai?
是的 長官 我們在馬德拉斯和孟加拉修的橋有半數是這類的
Yes, sir, half a dozen of them in Madras, Bengal....
如果這是你負責修建的大橋…
If this were your bridge...
你會怎樣來做…？
...how would you get it under way?
怎樣來做？
Get it under way, sir?
首先 我不會把它修在這
First of all, I wouldn't build it here.
噢 為什麼？
Oh, why not?
我可以說…
I was trying to tell you...
…小日本不可能再找到比這媮V糕的地點了
...the Japanese couldn't have picked a worse location.
你看到這些橋樁了嗎？
You see those piles?
他們正在下沉
They're sinking.
他們要經常受到壓力 而他們不可能支撐的住
We could drive those logs forever and they wouldn't hold.
那你會在哪堳媥禲H
Where would you build it?
下游較遠一點的地方 長官 在那些河道狹窄的地方跨越河流
Further downstream, sir. Across those narrows.
這樣兩岸都會有堅實的岩床
Then we'd have solid bedrock on both banks.
休斯 如果是你負責修建大橋 你會怎麼安排人手？
Hughes, if this were your bridge, how would you use the men?
絕對不是現在這樣子 正如你看到的 太混亂了
Not the way they're doing it. It's chaos, as you can see.
作業互不協調
Uncoordinated activity.
相互沒有配合
No teamwork.
很多組的工作相互制約
Some parties are working against each other.
是的
Yes.
我說 先生們 我們手上有個難題
I say, gentlemen, we have a problem on our hands.
感謝小日本所賜 我們在指揮一群烏合之眾
Thanks to the Japanese, we command a rabble.
沒有秩序 沒有原則
There's no order, no discipline.
- 我們的任務是要重組軍隊 - 是的 長官
- Our task is to rebuild the battalion. - Yes, sir.
那並不容易
Which isn't going to be easy.
幸運的是 我們手上有個對象 那座大橋
Fortunately, we have the means at hand. The bridge.
- 那座大橋 長官？ - 是的 那座大橋
- The bridge, sir? - The bridge.
我們要展示我們西方的效率 給他們上一課 讓他們出出醜
We'll teach them a lesson in Western efficiency that'll put them to shame.
展示我們英軍士兵的能力
Show what a British soldier is capable of.
是的 長官 我明白你的意思
Yes. I see your point, sir.
我知道這兒環境很艱苦…
I know how difficult it's going to be here...
…找不到合手的東西
...where you can't find what you need.
- 這是一個挑戰 - 請原諒 長官
- There's the challenge. - I beg your pardon, sir.
你真的要給他們修一座大橋？
You really want them to build the bridge?
你們平時可不是這麼遲鈍的
You're not usually so slow in the uptake.
我知道我們的戰士 必須讓他們有活幹
I know our men. You've got to keep them occupied.
如果他們沒有事幹 我們就找一些給他們做
If there weren't any work, we'd invent some.
- 我們會的 長官 - 我們很幸運
- That we would, sir. - So we're lucky.
但是我們還要把它造好
But it's going to be a proper bridge.
我還知道我們的戰士
Here again I know the men.
他們需要在工作中尋找自豪感
It's essential that they take pride in their job.
- 對不對 各位？ - 是的 長官
- Right, men? - Yes, sir.
堣 你是這堛疑鶬鉹H員 你在這堶n充當一個工程師
Reeves, you're the key man here as engineer.
告訴我你需要的 我們會盡量去滿足 我們能幹好嗎？
Tell me what you want and we'll get it. Can we make a go of it?
- 我們會幹的很漂亮的 長官 - 很好
- We'll do out best, sir. - Fine.
我們必須先制定計劃…
We must draw up our plans...
…然後和Saito開個會議…
...then arrange a conference with Saito...
…然後糾正他的錯誤
...and set him straight.
那些全是程序上的事情
That takes care of all the procedural matters.
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
下面我要說的可能相關的人員會不高興
The next point is unpleasant for all concerned, I'm afraid.
我不得不說 大橋的選址是草率的…
Sorry to say, the position of the bridge was fixed hastily...
…嗯 或者說是錯誤的
...and, I have to add, incorrectly.
錯誤的？
Incorrectly?
很不幸 是的
Unfortunately, yes.
我們的技術人員研究了你們選的地點…
Our engineer has made a study of the site...
…認為河床太軟
...and decided that the river bottom there is too soft.
太軟？
Too soft?
全是泥漿！ 所有的工作都是無用工
Mud! All the work has been useless.
- 堣 請你繼續 - 是的 長官
- Reeves, will you carry on? - Yes, sir.
橋墩的受力會把它們壓到水面以下的
Those piles of yours could be hammered below water level before they'd hold.
當第一列火車通過的時候 大橋就會倒塌
It would collapse under the first train.
這是壓力和泥土形變的圖表 單位是噸/平方英吋
The pressure and soil resistance figures in tons per square inch.
堣 在你深入介紹之前… 上校 我們可以來杯茶嗎？
Reeves, before you get too involved.... Colonel, could we have a cup of tea?
我認為大家都同意了 為了避免災難…
I take it we all agree that if we're to avoid disaster...
…我們必須在下游400碼的地方 在堣珙D選的地址上建一座新橋
...we build a new bridge, at the site picked by Reeves, 400 yards downstream.
現在我們來看下一個問題
Let's proceed to the next point.
我要改變他們的勞動強度
I decided to alter the work quota of our men.
- 改變勞動強度？ - 我要增加他們的勞動強度
- Alter? - I've increased it.
從挖土15碼改成2碼
From 1 .5 yards of earth moved to two.
你肯定會贊同這個決定
I'm sure it will meet with your approval.
休斯 你來詳細介紹一下
Hughes has all the facts. Would you take over?
我仔細研究了一下整個工程
I've done a time study of the entire project.
我認為 作業分配是錯誤的
You see, the available forces have been badly distributed.
我們應該修改作業分配
I'd urge we revise the organization of the working parties.
稍等一下 上校 我們邊吃邊談可能會節約時間
Just a moment. Colonel, it would save time if we could work during dinner.
我們可以有晚飯吃的吧？
Would it be possible to have dinner?
當然
Of course.
- 繼續 - 是 長官
- Carry on. - Yes, sir.
如果增加班組 細化分工…
If we increase the squads and specialize their functions...
…那麼 每天的工作量會增加30%
...l'm certain the total daily output can be increased by 30?0 .
現在 Saito 上校 我還有一點補充…
Now, Colonel Saito, I have one more point....
現在 還有一項決定刻不容緩
Now, there's another important decision that can't be postponed.
當英軍士兵在修橋的時候…
As the British will work on the bridge...
…修建鐵路的人手就少了
...only a few will be available for railway work.
你必須用你的人來支援鐵路的修建…
I must ask you to lend us some of your men to reinforce the railway gang...
…那樣 鋪軌的工作也能盡快的完成
...so the final stretch of track can be completed as quickly as possible.
我已經下令了
I have already given the order.
我們也必須改變你們的工作強度
We must fix the daily work quota for your men.
我曾想過定為每天15碼 這樣不會太過疲勞…
I thought to set it at 1 .5 yards so as not to overtire them...
…但是和我們一樣是不是更好一些？
...but isn't it best to be the same as ours?
這樣也會形成良性競爭
That would also create a healthy competitive spirit.
我已經下令了
I have already given the order.
我們會盡善盡美的 對不對 休斯？
We'll try to surpass that, won't we, Hughes?
我想今晚的議程就到這
I think that completes the agenda for tonight.
謝謝你的關注 Saito上校
Thank you, Colonel Saito, for your kind attention.
還有問題嗎？
Are there any other questions?
我有一個問題
One question.
你能在期限內完成大橋嗎？
Can you finish the bridge in time?
坦率地講 看起來是不可能的
Frankly, the consensus of opinion is that it's impossible.
當然我們要試一試
But we'll certainly give it a go.
別忘了 我們因為分歧而浪費了一個月…
Don't forget we wasted a month through an unfortunate disagreement...
…當然那不是我的錯
...for which I was not to blame.
還有什麼問題嗎？
Is there anything else?
沒有了
No.
謝謝 會議結束
Thank you. The meeting is closed.
- 晚安 - 晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
我希望這些小日本會感激我們所做的
I hope these Japanese appreciate what we're doing for them.
雖然現在我還沒有感覺到這一點
For now I'm not concerned with their appreciation.
- 晚安 科林普頓 - 晚安 長官
- Good night, Clipton. - Good night, sir.
另外 我想告訴你…
By the way, I meant to tell you...
…這埵酗@些樹比較像榆樹
...there are trees here similar to elm.
倫敦橋的榆樹樁已經支撐了600年了
And the elm piles of London Bridge lasted 600 years.
- 600年 堣牷H - 是的 長官
- Six hundred years, Reeves? - Yes, sir.
600年
Six hundred years.
真是奇跡
That would be quite something.
我在找一個美國人 他叫 捨爾斯
I'm looking for an American named Commander Shears.
- 在海灘上 - 謝謝
- Yes, down on the beach. - Oh, thank you very much.
吻一下！
Kiss!
那麼多人
Too many eyes.
你給了我藥粉 藥片 沐浴 注射 灌腸…
You give me powders, pills, baths, injections, enemas....
其實我只需要愛
All I need is love.
是的 你只需要愛
It's true. All you really need is love.
為什麼你這麼肯定你想病休？
Why are you so sure you'll get a medical discharge?
因為我內心堣@直是老百姓 寶貝
Because I'm a civilian at heart, lover.
而且我一直是性情中人
And I always follow my heart.
吻一下
Kiss.
怎麼會那樣 司令官？
How's that, commander?
不要叫我司令官
Don't call me commander.
太不浪漫了
It's unromantic.
你自己也是個軍官
You're an officer yourself.
你會喜歡我叫你寶貝上尉嗎？
How'd you like it if I called you Lieutenant Lover?
讓我們用平民的稱呼吧 就叫我"先生"吧
Let's be democratic. Just call me "sir."
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
厚顏無恥
Brass ahoy.
他來找你
He wants you. He's all yours.
- 我要去游泳了 - 別走！
- I'm going for a swim. - Don't leave me!
- 捨爾斯 司令官？ - 是的
- Commander Shears? - Yes.
我叫 華登
My name's Warden.
- 你好 - 對不起 打擾了…
- How do you do? - Sorry to intrude...
沒事 少校 我習慣了
That's okay, major. I'm used to it.
來點馬丁尼酒嗎？
Like a martini?
謝謝 不用了
That's very kind. I think not.
介意我來一點嗎？
Mind if I have one?
哪媟d來的？
How did you get that?
有醫院就有酒精
Where there's a hospital, there's alcohol.
噢 那當然
Yes, of course. Jolly good.
嗯 我盡量簡潔一些
Well, I'll be as brief as possible.
我隸屬於316部隊 那是個比較古怪的部門
I belong to a rather rum group called Force 31 6.
我們的總部在布坦尼可公園 (Botanical Gardens(植物園))
Our headquarters is in the Botanical Gardens.
- 保護稀有植物不被敵人破壞？ - 當然不是
- Protecting rare plants from the enemy? - Not quite.
- 你當真不來一點？ - 不 謝謝
- Sure you won't have one? - No, thanks.
我們對你工作過的鐵路很感興趣
We have an interest in that railway you worked on.
你可以給我們很多有價值的情報
You could give us no end of valuable information.
嗯 我已經離開那地方已經很多天了…
Well, I'm leaving for the States in a few days...
…而且我把所知的都告訴你們了
...and I told your people everything I know.
但是你可以用一種更特殊的方式來幫助我們
But you could help us in a rather special sense.
我知道有點強人所難 但是你能否出來去見一下我們？
I know it's a terrible imposition, but could you possibly come out and see us?
如果你想讓我再重複報告一遍的話
If you want to go over the whole thing again.
太好了 路易斯閣下會感激不盡的
Very kind. Lord Louis'll be grateful.
- 誰？ - 蒙巴頓
- Who? - Mountbatten.
我們是他的部下
We're one of his special pigeons.
那麼今晚怎麼樣？ 8點我會派一輛車來
Shall we say this evening, then? About 8. I'll send a car.
今晚？ 不行
This evening? Out of the question.
你明早怎麼樣？ 10點？
Tomorrow morning then? About 1 0?
- 好 就10點 - 多謝
- Okay, 1 0:00. - Thanks very much.
- 再見 - 再見
- Cheerio. - Cheerio.
祝你好運
Good luck.
謝謝
Thanks.
你很抱歉 你今晚要讓我空等了
You're sorry, but you're going to stand me up tonight.
大錯特錯
You couldn't be more wrong.
敬禮！
General salute!
舉槍致敬！
Present arms!
- 可以看你的通行證嗎？ - 好的
- May I see your pass, please? - Oh, yes.
華登少校的辦公室在路的盡頭
Major Warden's bungalow is at the end of the path.
幹得好 Jenkins 幹得好！
Good show, Jenkins. Good show!
快 湯姆森用你的匕首
Come along, Thomson. Use your knife, man.
站起來！快去指定地點
On your feet! Away to the debriefing room.
快 快點！
Come on, move yourselves! Move quickly!
動作太笨了 喬依斯
Very clumsy, Joyce, very clumsy.
要立即用匕首捅 喬依斯
Always use your knife immediately, Joyce.
你看 他佔了主動
You see, he's gained the initiative.
停下！ 對不起 長官
Wait a minute! I'm terribly sorry, sir.
- 你對不起？ - 是的
- You're sorry? - So am l.
- 我以為你是敵人 - 我是美國人 如果你是指這個的話
- I thought you were the enemy. - I'm American, if that's what you mean.
- 就這樣 喬依斯 - 是 長官 對不起 長官
- That'll be all, Joyce. - Yes, sir. Sorry, sir.
- 我能做什麼？ - 我要找華登上校
- What can I do for you? - I'm going to see Major Warden.
我來帶路 他現在應該快下課了
I'll show you the way. He'll finish his lecture any moment now.
- 他現在下課了 - 這麼大的聲音
- That's the end of his lecture. - Thunderous ovation.
他認為訓練越接近實戰越好
He believes in keeping our training as close to real life as possible.
- 華登少校 - 嗯？
- Major Warden, sir? - Yes?
很高興見到你
Good of you to come.
- 他們待你還好吧？ - 確實是的
- They took care of you? - They certainly have.
謝謝你 跟我來
Thank you, staff. Well, come along, then.
格林上校要見你
Col. Green is looking forward to meeting you.
- 這個地方還不錯吧？ - 我不知道這媮椄O一所軍事學校
- Fascinating place, isn't it? - Didn't know it was a commando school.
我們盡量不用這種稱呼 那樣會製造緊張空氣
We're trying to discourage the use of that word. Such a melodramatic air.
你在這媟F什麼？
What do you do here?
爆破 摧毀一類的事情
Sabotage, demolition, that line of country.
我們使用 PE 塑膠炸藥 很不錯的東西
We're using P.E., plastic explosives. It's wonderful.
剛才那個爆炸的炸藥只有這個一半大
That pop was made with a lump half this size.
只要硝化甘油炸藥的一半 而威力卻有兩倍
It's twice as powerful as gelignite at half the weight.
沒引爆的情況下是很安全的
It's quite harmless until it's detonated.
謝謝你的介紹
Thanks for telling me.
它完全防水 而且可塑性很好
It's completely waterproof and actually plastic.
看到嗎？你可以用它來做你想用它做的事情
See? You can do what you like with it.
這是我的辦公室
This is my place.
這
Go ahead.
喔 渴死了 我要來杯茶
Oh, I'm dying for a cup of tea.
- 你也來一杯？ - 不 謝謝
- Would you care for one? - No, thanks.
- 來杯酒？ - 不 謝謝
- A drink? - No, thank you.
- 給我來壺茶 彼得 - 是的 長官
- Pot of tea for one, please, Peter. - Very good, sir.
這個你也看得懂？
Do you read this?
戰前 我在劍橋教東方語言
I taught Oriental languages at Cambridge before the war.
我還沒有祝賀你的成功逃亡呢 幹得好！
I never congratulated you on your escape. Good show!
如果你的海上救援飛機沒有看到我 我也不會呆在這
If your sea rescue plane hadn't spotted me, I wouldn't be here.
是的 我想不會
No, I suppose not.
你願意再來看看你逃出來的地方嗎？
Would you like to see where you were?
好的
All right.
我們的情報很有限 主要來源於你的報告
Our information's scanty. It's based on your report.
我們認為戰俘營在這
We think the camp's here.
你們是否有尼科爾森上校的消息？
Do your people have any idea what happened to Col. Nicholson?
他很勇敢 要槍斃他時 他也不眨一下眼睛
He had guts. They were about to shoot him and he didn't bat an eye.
當你要被槍斃的時候 你本來就什麼也不能做
If you're about to be shot there's not much you can do.
這堿O桂河 這堿O你求助的村子
Here is the river Kwai, and here's the village where you were helped.
這堿O鐵路
Here is the railway.
你肯定非常熟悉這一帶
You must be fairly familiar with this area.
不 大部分時間我腦袋堨u是一片空白
No, I was out of my head half the time.
鐵路從新加坡開始 經過馬來西亞…
The railway starts down here in Singapore. Malaya...
…曼谷 仰光 他們想一直貫通到印度
...Bangkok, Rangoon. Their idea is to drive on through, into lndia.
- 我是在哪堻Q救起的？ - 在這堛近
- Where was I picked up? - Oh, about here.
日軍想在五月中旬貫通曼谷和仰光
The Japanese aim to open the Bangkok-  Rangoon section by the middle of May.
我們必須阻止他們
We'll try to prevent them.
太遠了 轟炸機飛不到這
It's too far for bombers to carry a load.
我們必須用地面部隊把它摧毀
We'll have to go smash it on the ground.
- 那你想怎麼辦？ - 空降之後 徒步到那
- How? - Parachute drop, then march.
帶著爆破裝置穿過雨林嗎？
With demolition equipment through that jungle?
我們的主要問題是對那堣@無所知
Our chief problem is lack of firsthand knowledge.
我們沒有人到過哪
You see, none of us have ever been there.
- 我其實不想讓你失望 但是… - 那很有趣
- I don't want to discourage... - It should be interesting.
格林上校把桂河大橋交給我了 我要帶一隊人去炸掉它
Col. Green's given me the Kwai bridge. I'm taking a team in to blow it up.
你真幸運
Lucky you.
你真的不想來點茶？
Sure you won't have tea?
不 謝謝 我不想失禮 但是我在2點鐘要和一個漂亮的姑娘約會
No, thanks. I don't want to be rude, but I've got a date at 2.
- 如果還有問題的話… - 很抱歉 是的
- If there are any questions.... - Of course, I'm sorry.
嗯 只有一個問題
Well, there is only one question, actually.
你覺得再去哪堣@趟怎麼樣？
How would you feel about going back?
什麼？
Come again?
在某種情況下 有點兒…
Under the circumstances it's a bit much...
…但是你是我們完成這個任務的關鍵
...but you have a unique knowledge for our purpose.
我們很希望你能和我們一起去
We'd love to have you with us.
這就是你找我來這堛滬鴞]？
That's why you brought me here?
來請我再去哪堣@趟？
To ask me this?
嗯 坦率的說 是的
Well, frankly, yes.
我才從那堸k出來
I just got out of there.
我能從那堸k出來 簡直是個奇跡 而你現在卻讓我再回去！ 真荒唐！
My escape was a miracle. Now you want me to go back! Ridiculous!
我知道這很令人為難…
This is embarrassing...
我不屬於你們的部隊 我隸屬於美國海軍
I don't belong to you. I belong to the American Navy.
事實上 格林上校和你的部隊討論過這件事
Actually, Col. Green has taken the matter up with your people.
- 和我的部隊？ - 你的海軍把你轉借給我們
- With my people? - Your Navy's turned you over to us.
昨天早上 從太平洋艦隊指揮部來了一個命令…
A signal arrived yesterday morning from the Pacific...
確認把你暫借給316部隊
...authorizing your temporary transfer of duty to Force 31 6.
- 他們不能這樣做！ - 恐怕他們不這樣認為
- They can't do this! - I'm afraid they have.
很遺憾告訴你這個消息
It was hard to break it to you.
但是他們不能這樣對我 海軍搞錯了！
But they can't do this to me. I mean it. My Navy's made a mistake!
你看 我不是海軍司令官 我甚至不是一名軍官
Look. I'm not a Navy commander. I'm not even an officer.
整個事情都不是真的 我只是一個擦炮筒的普通士兵
The whole thing's a fake. I'm just an ordinary swab jockey, second class.
當休斯頓號沉沒的時候 我和一名真正的司令官上岸
When the Houston sunk, I made it ashore with a real commander.
我們碰上了日軍巡邏隊 他被打死了
We ran into a Japanese patrol. He was killed.
我認為只是時間問題 直到我…
I figured it was just a matter of time till l...
所以你和死人換了服裝
So you changed uniforms with a dead man.
我認為在戰俘營中軍官會受到較好的待遇
I thought officers would get better treatment in prison camps.
但是我遇到的Saito 他命令指揮官和其他人一起勞動
But with Saito, the officers worked along with the rest.
總是有意想不到的事情 對不對？
There's always the unexpected, isn't there?
我已經有點習慣當司令官了…
I kind of got used to being a commander...
…所以當我來到醫院的時候…
...so when I arrived at the hospital...
…我看了一下普通戰士的病房和指揮官的病房…
...l took a look at the enlisted men's ward and then the officer's ward...
…然後我對自己說 "就繼續冒充一些時間吧"
...and I said to myself, " Let's let it ride along for a while."
軍官還真有優待
There were certain advantages.
我在海灘上就看到一個
I saw one of them on the beach.
這就是整個故事
That's the whole story.
問題是 你不能用我 你需要的是一名指揮官…
The point is, you can't use me. You want an officer...
…一個並不存在的美軍司令官捨爾斯
...an American Commander Shears who doesn't exist.
當海軍發現了真相 他們會說:
When the Navy learns the truth, they'll say:
"由於假扮指揮官 把他遣送回家"
"Ship him home for impersonating an officer."
- 一旦結果是那樣 我就成功了 - 你就怎樣？
- Once that happens, I've got it made. - Got it what?
成功了！ 我現在想喝點酒
Made! I'd like that drink now.
我想申請病退
I'll apply for a medical discharge.
我會說假裝指揮官是由於在森林中得了神經病
I'll say I impersonated an officer because I went crazy in the jungle.
甚至 有時我覺得我是海爾森海軍艦隊司令
I'm getting worse. Sometimes I think I'm Admiral Halsey.
很聰明的計劃
It's quite a clever plan.
不僅僅是是聰明的計劃 而且是簡單安全的
Not only clever, it's foolproof.
如果海軍發現了我的真實身份
If my Navy finds out who I am...
那份命令就是一張廢紙
...those orders won't be worth the paper they're written on.
這是你的照片嗎？
Isn't this your photograph?
- 從哪媟d到的？ - 由於你的部隊不能確認你的身份…
- Where did you get this? - It took some doing...
…就費了些事
...since your people couldn't identify you.
最後你的太平洋艦隊發了一份你的服役檔案過來
Finally your C- in- C Pacific sent us a copy of your service record.
照片和指紋 你願意看看嗎？
The photograph, fingerprints. Would you care to have a look?
我們知道你的真實身份已經有一個星期了
You see, we've known about your actual rank for nearly a week.
你的海軍處在一個兩難的境地
Your Navy's in an awkward position.
一方面你是個英雄…
In one sense you're a hero...
…成功逃出雨林
...for making an escape from the jungle.
同時 因為你假扮指揮官
At the same time, they can't bring you home...
他們又不好把你送回家 然後頒發一枚海軍十字勳章給你
...and give you the Navy Cross for impersonating an officer.
我想因此他們很樂意把你轉交給我們
I suppose that's why they were happy to hand you over.
你明白了嗎？
You see?
棘手的問題
Hot potato.
說到你的軍階
As far as your rank is concerned...
在316部隊 我們並不在意那個
...we're fairly informal about that in Force 31 6.
你可以假裝你是少校
You'd have the simulated rank of major.
假裝上校 那意味著…
A simulated major. That figures.
嗯…
Well....
我最好是志願參加
As long as I'm hooked, I might as well volunteer.
很好！
Good show!
格林上校 長官
Oh, Colonel Green, sir.
這是捨爾斯上校 他志願幫助我們炸掉那座橋
This is Major Shears. He volunteered to go and help me blow up the bridge.
真的？
Really?
很好！
Good show!
太好了 上校！
Jolly good show, major!
去醫務室吧 這隻腳感染了
Get up to sick bay. This foot's infected.
上校會以為我在裝病
Colonel might think I'm malingering.
我是醫療官快去吧！
I'm the medical officer. Get cracking!
有人願意告訴我為什麼他想建一座真的大橋嗎？
Will someone tell me why he wants to build a proper bridge?
不要擔心老尼克他知道自己在幹什麼
Don't worry about old Nick. He knows what he's doing.
嘿 柯林普頓該給我們展示一下了
Hello, Clipton. About time you paid us a visit.
我們的小伙子幹得真不錯
Fine job our chaps are doing.
是的 他怎麼樣？
Yes. How's he behaving?
當我們接管過來以後 他已經變得很講理了
He's been most reasonable since we took over.
- 他在想什麼？ - 我不清楚
- What's he thinking? - I haven't the foggiest.
- 謝謝你 堣 - 好的 長官
- Thanks, Reeves. - Right, sir.
你怎麼看？
What do you think?
絕對是個挑戰 對不對？
Quite a challenge, isn't it?
你真認為建這座橋是個好主意嗎？
Are you convinced that building this bridge is a good idea?
- 你是認真的嗎？ - 是的 長官
- Are you serious? - Yes, sir.
一個好主意嗎？ 我們再看看
A good idea? Take another look.
你不認為他們士氣很高嗎？ 你不認為軍紀又得到恢復了嗎？
You don't agree morale is high? Discipline has been restored?
你不認為他們的待遇得到提高了嗎？
Their condition has improved?
他們難道沒有更快樂了一些了嗎？
Are they a happier lot or aren't they?
他們吃得也好了 再也得不到虐待
They feed better and they are no longer abused.
坦率地說 柯林普頓 有時我一點也不瞭解你
Honestly, Clipton, there are times when I don't understand you at all.
讓我說得更清楚一些
I'll try to make myself clear.
事實上 我們所作的事情可以被理解為…
The fact is, what we're doing could be construed as...
…對不起 長官 是通敵合作
...forgive me, sir, collaboration with the enemy.
甚至可以被認為是叛國罪
Perhaps even treason.
我們是戰俘 我們沒有權利拒絕勞動
We're prisoners of war. We haven't the right to refuse to work.
我知道 長官 但是我們一定要做得這麼好嗎？
I understand that, sir. But must we work so well?
我們一定要做得比他們自己還好嗎？
Must we do better than they could themselves?
如果你替Saito做手術 你是會盡力治好他還是殺死他？
If you had to operate on Saito, would you do your best or let him die?
你難道不認為懶散會擊垮我們？
Would you prefer we disintegrate in idleness?
讓世人說我們連一件正常的工作都不會做？
Or have it said we can't do a proper job?
這很重要 要讓他們知道 他們不可能在身體或精神上打垮我們
It's important to show them they can't break us in body or in spirit.
好好看看 柯林普頓
Take a good look, Clipton.
有一天 當戰爭結束
One day the war will be over.
我希望將來那些使用這座橋的人…
I hope that those who use the bridge in years to come...
…會記住它是怎麼樣被建成的 是誰修建了他們
...will remember how it was built, and who built it.
不是一群奴隸 而是一群戰士 是一群英國戰士 甚至是在被俘的情況下修建的
Not a gang of slaves, but soldiers. British soldiers, even in captivity.
- 是的 長官 - 你是一個好醫生
- Yes, sir. - You're a fine doctor...
但是對於戰爭 你還要學習很多
...but you've a lot to learn about the army.
抓住他！ 抓住他！
Hold him! Hold him!
用腳！
Use your boot! Get your boot in there, will you?
早上好！
Good morning!
你們到底在看什麼？
What on earth are you people staring at?
用腳踹倒他！
Get him with your boot!
對不起我來遲了 長官
I'm sorry I'm late, sir.
遲到4分鐘 你在做內科檢查嗎？
Four minutes, to be exact. You were in need of medical attention?
- 對不起 長官？ - 我是指那個女護士
- Sir? - I was referring to the nurse.
足智多謀 華登 說的一點也不錯
Very ingenious. Warden was right.
請坐
Sit down.
我請你來這 是要你挑選行動小組堛熔艦|個人
I asked you here to help us pick the fourth member of your team.
- 請喬伊斯先生進來 - 是的 長官
- Ask Mr. Joyce to come in. - Yes, sir.
查普曼想要喬伊斯 但是我有疑慮
Chapman wants Joyce, but I have my doubts.
他有太多的想像力了
He has too much imagination as distinct from cold calculation.
我已經告訴過你…
I've told you...
…在這個任務中 總會有萬一
...in this job, even when it's finished there's always one more thing to do.
他在學校堿O游泳最好的
He's the best swimmer in the school.
我早已清楚你的觀點 我現在要捨爾斯的意見
I'm well aware of your evaluation. The opinion I want is Shears'.
好的 稍息
All right, at ease.
這些人想帶你到雨林一遊
These men are thinking of taking you for a hike in the jungle.
是的 長官
Yes, sir.
你在蒙特利爾是個會計師？
You were an accountant in Montreal?
是的 長官 但還不是個正式的會計師
Yes, sir. Not really an accountant.
因為我還沒有得到許可證
That is, I didn't have my charter.
那麼你實際上做什麼呢？
Exactly what did you do?
嗯 長官 我只是核算數據…
Well, sir, I just checked columns and columns of figures...
…核算那些別人核算過的數據…
...which people had checked before me...
…然後別人再核算我核算過的數據
...and other people checked them after I had checked them.
- 聽起來很煩人 - 長官 是很煩人
- Sounds a frightful bore. - Sir, it was a bore.
你怎麼會在這堛滿H
How did you wind up here?
1939年 我去倫敦應徵 後來 我志願來到這
In '39 I came over to London to enlist. Later I volunteered for this work.
- 你是志願的！ - 是的 長官 你看 正規部隊…
- You volunteered! - Yes, sir. See, the regular Army...
請繼續 你可以很坦率地說
Go ahead, you can be frank.
嗯 正規部隊使我回想起我原來的工作
Well, the regular Army reminded me of my job in civilian life.
他們不需要你去思考
They don't expect you to think.
那你思考這個看看
Think about this.
你能用它來殺人嗎？
Are you sure you'd be able to use it in cold blood?
我知道怎麼使用它
I know how to use it.
不是那意思 我問你能用它來殺人嗎？
That's not what I meant. Could you use it in cold blood?
你可以毫不猶豫地殺人嗎？
Could you kill without hesitation?
這個問題我曾經問過自己 它很困擾我
That's a question I've asked myself. It's worried me quite a bit.
那麼答案是什麼？
And what was the answer?
事實上 我並不知道答案 長官
I don't honestly know, sir.
我曾經試圖想像自己…
I've tried to imagine myself....
我很難使自己相信殺戮不是犯罪
I suppose I find it hard to kid myself that killing isn't a crime.
那是軍隊堛漱@個古老的問題
It's an old army problem.
嗯 好了 謝謝你 喬伊斯
Well, I think that's all. Thank you, Joyce.
我可以參加行動了嗎？
Am I to go with the team?
我們會讓你知道的
We'll let you know.
你們看到了吧
You see what I mean.
嗯 至少他是誠實的
Well, at least he was honest.
不到那時候 我們誰也不知道答案
None of us ever know the answer to that question until the moment arises.
你的意見呢 捨爾斯？
What's your opinion, Shears?
嗯 他是加拿大人
Well, he's Canadian.
正好吻合我們這個多國組合行動
That fits with the international composition of this outfit.
如果他想去 他可以替我去！
If he wants to go, he can take my place!
嗯 如果大家都同意喬伊斯去 那就讓他們參加吧
Well, if you're all agreed on Joyce, he's yours.
我們對那個村莊進行了空中偵察
I had an air reconnaissance report on the village.
你們可以在晚上空降到那
There's enough clearing to make your jump at dusk.
- 你經過跳傘訓練嗎？ - 沒有 長官
- You've had parachute training? - No, sir.
該死！ 這個可麻煩了
Blast! This is awkward.
從來沒遇到過這樣的事情！
Silly, it never occurred to me!
也許 我可以不…
Well, maybe...
我們可以給他安排一些訓練
He's right. Arrange some practice jumps for him.
我現在就去安排
I'll go check right away.
- 好的 查普曼 你也可以走了 - 是的 長官
- All right, Chapman, you can run along. - Yes, sir.
嗯 是不是很簡單？
Well, feel like a sniff of air?
是的 長官
Yes, sir.
你不知道你是多麼的重要
You don't realize what a plum you are.
你熟悉那地區 你和那村莊堛漱H結交朋友
Your knowledge of the area, making friends in that village.
就好像整個逃跑 都是我們計劃好的
It's almost as if your whole escape had been planned with us in mind.
這埵釣ヰF西 你可能會感興趣 新的" L"藥片
By the way, here's something that'll interest you. The new " L" pill.
- " L"藥片？ - 致命毒藥 迅速 無痛
- L pill? - L for lethal. Instant, painless.
比老的型號要好很多 當然是為了被俘時使用
Much better than the old ones. For capture, of course.
你是想告訴我不要被活捉
You're telling me not to be taken alive.
算我沒說
I wouldn't recommend it.
如果你們誰受傷了 其他人會把他扔在身後的
If any of you get hurt or wounded the others will have to leave him behind.
在這次行動中 炸毀目標是第一要務
The objective comes first in our work.
你想聽我對這小組的真實評價嗎？ 在他們面前我沒有說
You want my honest evaluation? I didn't want to say in front of them.
我明白 請講
I understand, go ahead.
嗯 查普曼很好 在他血管堿y的是冰水
Well, Chapman will be fine. Ice water in his veins.
喬伊斯 嗎… 他會好的
Joyce is.... He'll be okay.
- 華登 我覺得不行 - 為什麼？
- It's Warden I don't get. - Oh? Why not?
他只是個劍橋老師
Cambridge don and all of that.
他就像個玩鞭炮的孩子…
It's one thing to play with explosives like a kid with firecrackers...
他經驗很豐富的
He's not without experience, you know.
當新加坡陷落的時候 他在後面炸掉了幾座大橋
When Singapore fell, he stayed behind to blow up a couple of bridges.
還在小日本抓住他之前 安裝了好幾個裝置
Many other installations before the Japs caught him.
- 真精彩 他… - 長官 有些麻煩
- Fascinating story. He... - Sir, it's most annoying.
從時間上考慮 他們認為練習跳傘意義不大
In view of time, they don't think practice jumps would be worth it.
如果你跳一次 只有50%機會受傷
If you make one jump there's only a 50?0 chance of injury.
跳兩次 80% 3次 他肯定要受傷
Two jumps, 80?0. Three jumps, you're bound to get your packet.
大家的一致的結論是 最好的辦法就是讓捨爾斯…
The consensus is, the most sensible thing for Shears to do...
不要訓練 直接去跳下去
...is to go ahead and jump and hope for the best.
帶不帶降落傘？
With or without parachute?
噢 很好！
Oh, very good!
帶不帶降落傘！
With or without!
他掛在樹上！
He's in the trees!
Yai 說我們不能從你的那條路去桂河
Yai says we can't reach the Kwai your way.
有太多的日軍崗哨 我們要迂迴到北方穿越原始森林
There are too many Japanese patrols. We'll swing north through heavy jungle.
- 那麼誰帶路？ - Yai
- Then who's going to lead? - Yai.
他恨日本人 他們抓走了這堜狾釭漕k人
He hates the Japanese. They took all his men.
我們必須用婦女來幫我們搬東西
Which means we shall have to use women bearers.
- 婦女！ - 她們能勝任的
- Women bearers! - They're capable.
他說在這媢L夜很危險
He says it's dangerous to spend the night here.
3里外有個日軍崗哨 所以我們要在森林媞恅惜F
There's an enemy post three miles away so we'll have to sleep in the jungle.
- 查普曼怎麼辦？ - Yai會把他和傘埋起來
- What about Chapman? - Yai will bury him and his chute.
有什麼問題嗎？
Is there something wrong?
我正在想你會說他們的語言 而我不會
I was just thinking. You speak Yai's language. I don't.
他要帶路走我從未走過的路
He's going to lead you to the river by a route I never took.
那麼還要我來幹什麼呢？
Will someone tell me why I'm so indispensable to this outfit?
我知道你的感受 但事情總有萬一 對不對？
I know how you feel, but there's always the unexpected, isn't there?
和查普曼講萬一吧
Tell that to Chapman.
我們開始行動吧！
Let's get cracking!
你很可愛
You're lovely.
可  愛
Lovely.
工作愉快！
Be happy in your work!
是 長官
Yes, sir.
螞蝗
Leeches.
她讓你別動她會把你背上的螞蝗弄下來
She's telling you to hold still. She'll take the leeches off your back.
像你這樣的女孩怎麼能在這種地方呢？
What's a girl like you doing in a place like this?
我會教你說暹羅語
I'll teach you to say that in Siamese.
不 太多的交談會壞事
No, that would spoil it. Too much talk always spoils it.
那玩意兒怎麼了？
What's wrong with that thing?
信號太弱了
It's taken an awful beating. I can't get a strong signal.
因為這堣S濕又霉！ 雨林堜狾釭漱@切都是這樣
I'll tell you. It's wet, mildewed! Like everything else in this jungle.
你最好把它扔掉！
You might as well dump it!
這堿O東京電台 廣播結束
This is Radio Tokyo signing off.
提醒您不要緊張…
This is your friendliest enemy reminding you to take it easy...
…不要盲動
...and never volunteer for anything.
如果我們還呆在這 我們就出不去了
If we stay, we'll be up to our necks.
- 就快譯好了 長官 - 快讀！
- I've got it all decoded, sir. - Read it!
是 長官 "1 原來說的大橋已經不再建了
Yes, sir. "One, original bridge works reported abandoned.
在原址下游的地方 在建新的大橋
New construction downstream from first site.
2 敵人想在通車典禮上從曼谷到仰光
Two, enemy intends to open railway with passage of special train...
開出一列專列…滿載軍隊和重要人物
...Bangkok for Rangoon with troops and V.I.P.
估計在13號上午到達目的地
Estimated to arrive target, a.m. 1 3th.
3 同時要炸掉專列
Three, synchronize demolition with passage of train.
4 好好幹 玩的開心" 就是這些
Four, good hunting. Have fun." That's all.
一列火車和一座大橋！
A train and a bridge!
我們能及時趕到那媔 長官？
Can we get there in time, sir?
Yai說我們還有2- 3天的路程
Yai says we're two to three days away.
如果我們快走的話 我們會在12號日落前趕到那
If we set a faster pace, we could make it before sundown on the 1 2th.
搭上一列火車 很值
It's worth it for the train.
好 我們要盡一切辦法 好好幹 玩的開心
Oh, by all means. Good hunting. Good show.
玩的開心 幹得很好
Jolly good fun. Jolly good.
如果你沒有修好收音機 我們就不會知道還有一列火車
If you hadn't fixed the radio, we wouldn't know about the train.
總有萬一 對不對？
There's always the unexpected, isn't there?
- 半品脫 長官 - 奎寧
- Half a pint, sir. - Quinine.
嗯 我們回頭再弄
Well, we'll complete this later.
- 柯林普頓 我們遇到一個問題 - 是嗎 長官？
- Clipton, we're facing a crisis. - Yes, sir?
我與堣 和休斯談過 我們不可能及時建好大橋
I spoke with Reeves and Hughes. We can't finish the bridge on time.
我們人力不夠
We haven't the manpower.
我已經請指揮官參加勞動 但是還不夠
I've asked the officers to help, but that won't do it.
指揮官也在幹活？
The officers are working?
我解釋了情況 他們志願參加 但是人還不夠
I explained the situation and they volunteered, but it's not enough.
為什麼不向 Saito要求一些人？
Why not ask Saito for some men?
這是我們的任務 要用我們自己最大的資源
This is ours. We'll make the most of our resources.
這就是我為什麼來和你談 我要病人名單
That's why I came to talk to you. The sick list.
這堻ㄛO病人
There's not a man in this hospital who doesn't belong there.
我並不是責備你 但總有一些人要裝病
It's no reflection on you, but there are always a few malingerers.
保持警惕 這就是我要說的
Keep an open mind, that's all I ask.
過來 我們來看看
Come along, let's see.
別動 別動
Don't move, don't move.
Haskins什麼病？
What's wrong with Haskins?
阿米巴痢疾和發燒 104度
Amoebic dysentery and black water fever. Temperature of 1 04.
好的 我知道了
Right. I see.
這個人呢？
And this man?
腿部潰瘍 如果我昨天多切一點的話 就可以保住這條腿
Leg ulcers. I may be able to save it if I do more cutting tonight.
要把他派去勞動嗎？
Want to send him out to work?
不許胡說八道 柯林普頓
Don't talk rot, Clipton.
那個人呢？
That man there?
胳膊感染
His arm's infected.
這些人的傷大多數都不會徹底痊癒
Most of their wounds won't heal properly.
我在想 新鮮空氣和輕微的勞動 會比關在這籠子埵n些
I wonder if fresh air and light duties might do more than being cooped up.
- 輕微的勞動？ - 因為擦傷胳膊就把他放在這堙K
- Light duties? - It's not our policy to keep a man...
- 不符合我們的原則 - 不符合我們的原則？
- ...just because he scratched his arm. - Not our policy?
即使狀態不佳 但是還是可以利用的
A man may not be on top of his form, but he can still be useful.
比如清理焊縫啦 收拾現場啦 稍息 貝克
Trimmings and finishing jobs. Stand easy, Baker.
你想去橋上做些輕微的工作嗎？
Do you feel up to doing a little light work on the bridge?
- 隨您吩咐 長官 - 很好
- Anything you say, sir. - Good show.
你呢？ 有困難嗎
You? Nothing difficult.
- 我會盡力 長官 - 好樣的
- I'll try, sir. - Good man.
同志們 不言而喻 我以你們為榮
Look here, men. It goes without saying that I'm proud of all of you.
但是我們現在遇到困難 如果你們覺得自己能行的話
But we're facing a crisis. For those of you who feel up to it...
能援助我們一下嗎？ 做一些力所能及的事情 搬搬弄弄 塗塗抹抹？
...how about lending us a hand? Fetch and carry, paint here and there?
怎麼樣？
What do you say?
- 是的 長官 - 好樣的 跟我來吧
- Yes, sir. - Good show. Come on, follow me.
10分鐘
Ten minutes.
要確認他們全都死了
Make sure they're all dead.
跟我來 喬伊斯
Come on, Joyce.
用匕首 否則我們會打到自己人
Use your knife or we'll be shooting each other.
走那邊 喬伊斯
Go that way, Joyce.
我可以幹掉他的 我已經準備好了
I could have done it. I was ready.
你受傷了 長官？
Are you hit, sir?
走
Let's go.
只是表面傷 不會有骨折
It's superficial. Maybe a chipped bone, but nothing broken.
- 是我的錯 長官 - 噢 住嘴
- It's my fault, sir. - Oh, shut up.
我可以走的不很嚴重
I can walk on it. That's all that counts.
是啊 但是還有多遠 我們能走多快呢？
Yeah, but how far and how fast?
不試不知道 對不對？
We won't know that till I've tried it, will we?
你在幹什麼？
What are you doing?
我沒有命令停止
I didn't give orders for a halt.
我們都需要休息一下
We all need it.
我們還要5小時急行軍才能到達目標
We're still five hours' fast march from the objective.
也許要6小時
Maybe six.
快
Come on.
如果你一直走的話 你會流血不止而死的
If you keep walking, you'll bleed to death.
- 你們必須把我留在這 - 你停下來 我們就停下來
- You're going to leave me here. - If you stop, we stop.
你不可能在夜堿膍s大橋的結構
You can't study the layout of the bridge after dark.
你們必須在日落前趕到那
You've got to get there before sundown.
但是 長官 任務結束後 我們不能保證順這條路返回…
But, sir, when the job's done, who knows if we can return by this route...
即使我們走這條路 也不能保證找到你
...or whether we could find you if we did?
如果我是你的話 你知道的 我就一點也不猶豫就會離開你
If you were me, I wouldn't hesitate to leave you and you know that.
他不知道 但是我知道
He doesn't know, but I do.
你會把你媽媽拋棄在這堛 如果規則要求這樣的話
You'd leave your own mother here if the rules called for it.
你們必須繼續前進這是命令
You'll go on without me. That's an order.
捨爾斯 現在由你來指揮
You're in command now, Shears.
我不遵守這條命令
I won't obey that order.
你的英雄主義讓我噁心
Your heroics make me sick.
你們都帶著死亡的臭氣
You carry the stench of death like the plague.
爆炸 L藥片
Explosives and L- pills go well together.
不是這個就是那個 要麼毀掉大橋 要麼毀掉自己
It's one thing or the other. Destroy a bridge or destroy yourself.
這場戰爭只是個遊戲
This is just a game, this war.
你和那個尼科爾森上校都有瘋狂的勇氣 為了什麼？
You and that Colonel Nicholson. You're crazy with courage. For what?
怎樣才能死的像個紳士 怎樣死才符合規矩…
How to die like a gentleman, how to die by the rules...
而問題是要怎樣才能像個人那樣活著！
...when the only important thing is how to live like a human being!
我不會讓你死在這堛 華登…
I'm not gonna leave you here to die, Warden...
因為我才不管你那個什麼大橋或者你的什麼規則
...because I don't care about your bridge or about your rules.
如果我們繼續前進 我們就一塊走
If we go on, we go on together.
老Yai 幹得好
Good old Yai.
好的
All right.
快過來
Come on.
我們走近些
Let's get closer.
還在耿耿於懷我們帶你一起來嗎？
Still sorry we brought you along?
- 感覺好點了嗎？ - 是的
- Feeling better? - Yeah.
現在還由你指揮
You're in command again, you know.
謝謝 上校
Thank you, major.
真奇怪這是一座堅固的 設計得很好的大橋
I can't understand it. It's such a solid, well- designed job.
並不像敵人一貫拼湊的的那種東西
Not like the bridges the enemy usually throws together.
看
Look.
下面那些可憐的小鬼子
Those poor devils down there.
可以想像他們被逼著在這樣的條件下建橋的情景
Imagine being forced to build that in the condition they must be in.
還有英國軍官在地上工作
They've got a British officer working on his knees.
小日本好像很高興
The Japanese seem to be enjoying it too.
如果他知道我們在這 肯定可以鼓舞他的士氣
If he knew we were here, it might boost his morale.
如果不是也要炸那火車 我們就可以設置個定時炸彈 然後跑到幾里之外
If not for the train, we could set a time fuse and be miles away.
我們不知道火車明天是什麼時間通過這堙K
Since we don't know what time it'll cross tomorrow...
我們不得不手動引爆炸藥
...we'll have to do the job manually.
我們可以把炸藥填在橋墩3尺水面下
We'll set the charges against the piles...
我想…
...about three feet underwater, I should think...
把主線纜布到下游引爆者那
...and run the main wire downstream to the plunger.
問題是引爆者應該藏在哪堙H
The problem is where to hide it.
我們這一邊河流很顯然被日軍佔用
Our side of the river is obviously used by the Japanese.
他們一眼就能發現
They'd spot it at once.
看 你們看到那些樹段和它們下面的岩石了嗎？
Look. Do you see those fallen tree trunks?
在那邊的小沙灘上？
And the grey rock just below them on that little beach?
- 是的 長官 我看到他們了 - 那奡N是我們的引爆位置
- Yes, sir, I see them. - That's our key position.
雖然在河的那邊…
The wrong side of the river...
…但是是在有效距離內的唯一藏身之處
...but it's the only hiding place within feasible distance.
當橋被引爆之後…
As soon as the bridge goes up...
…那個人必須游回來
...whoever's there will have to swim back.
這樣游泳可不好受
It won't be a pleasant swim.
長官 我的游泳技術是最好的
Sir, I was the best swimmer in my course.
看來只能是你了
It looks like your line of country, then.
謝謝
Thank you.
捨爾斯 在這個岸邊找個地方掩護喬伊斯
Shears, pick a spot on our side of the bank where you can cover Joyce.
Yai會和你一起 當小日本發現喬伊斯時
Yai will be with you so you can occupy the Nips...
你們可以幫助他
...if they make trouble for Joyce.
理論上總有萬一…
On the theory that there's always one more thing...
我也會在這邊用迫擊炮牽制他們的
...l'll set up the mortar here to create an additional diversion.
甚至我還可以對火車來幾下
Perhaps I might even take a few potshots at the train.
都明白了嗎？
All clear?
還有問題嗎？ 好的 你天一黑就行動
Any questions? Right, you'll start as soon as it's dark.
他們肯定在橋上有崗哨…
They're sure to have sentries on the bridge...
所以你必須從上游把炸藥送過去
...so you'll have to float the stuff down from upriver...
也就是說要扎一個筏子
...which means building a raft.
Yai.
Yai會帶3個婦女幫助你
Yai will take three women to help you.
還有一個要和我呆在一起 好 開始行動！
One will stay here with me. All right, get cracking!
你知道 如果不是腳踝受傷 喬伊斯的任務就是我的了
You know, if it wasn't for my ankle, I'd take Joyce's assignment.
你認為他行嗎？
You think he'll be all right?
我覺得可以 要我來處理嗎？
I think so. Want me to handle it?
如果可以的話 我會讓你和迫擊炮呆在一起
I'd let you stay up here with the mortar if I could.
對不起
I'm sorry.
結束之後 我希望你能得到病休…
When it's over, I hope you get that medical discharge...
而且是毫不困難地得到
...and not the hard way.
謝謝
Thanks.
裝彈
Load.
真漂亮
Beautiful.
是的 很漂亮
Yes, beautiful.
一流的工程
A first- rate job.
我從未想到會做得這麼好
I had no idea it would turn out so well.
是啊 幹得很漂亮
Yes, a beautiful creation.
我一直在想…
I've been thinking....
明天就是我服役28年
Tomorrow it will be 28 years to the day that I've been in the service.
28年的和平與戰爭
Twenty- eight years in peace and war.
我呆在家堛漁伅﹞ㄥW過10個月
I haven't been at home more than ten months in all that time.
當然 這仍然是完美的人生
Still, it's been a good life.
我熱愛印度
I love lndia.
我不可能從頭再來
I wouldn't have had it any other way.
但是 有時候…
But there are times....
突然你會意識到你又回到了起點
Suddenly you realize you are nearer the end than the beginning.
而你感到彷徨…
And you wonder....
你問自己…
You ask yourself...
…人生的意義是什麼…
...what the sum total of your life represents...
…這樣和那樣又有什麼差別…
...what difference your being there at any time made to anything...
...or if it made any difference at all, really.
與其他的職業比起來
Particularly in comparison with other men's careers.
我不知道這樣想是否正確的…
I don't know if that kind of thinking's healthy...
但是我必須承認 我一直在思考這些問題
...but I must admit I've had some thoughts on those lines...
...from time to time.
但 今晚…
But tonight....
今晚…
Tonight....
糟糕
Blast.
我得走了
I must be off.
他們在準備一些娛樂活動
The men are preparing some sort of entertainment.
真可愛
Lovely.
如果你是
If you were the only
世上唯一的女孩
Girl in the world
你是世上唯一男孩
And you were the only boy
其他的一切都不重要
Nothing else would matter
在今天
In the world today
我們要相愛
We could go on loving
用古老的方式
In the same old way
伊甸園只是為兩個人而建
A Garden of Eden just made for two
我代表大家說幾句…
I'm sure I speak for all of us...
這是一個愉快的夜晚
...when I say this has been a most enjoyable evening.
明天你們大多數都要轉移到一個新的戰俘營 開始新的工作
Most of you move on tomorrow to a new camp and new construction.
很遺憾你們看不到大橋的首次使用
It's a pity you won't see the first practical use of this bridge.
你們會很高興的知道這座大橋
You'll be glad to know that the completion...
所連接的鐵路
...of this link in the railway...
可以讓我們用火車來
...will enable us to transport the sick and disabled...
把傷病員運輸到新的營地
...to the new camp by train.
Saito上校善意的允許
Colonel Saito has kindly permitted me to stay behind...
我和柯林普頓上校留在最後
...with Major Clipton and the sick men...
幾天後我們就會會合
...and we'll rejoin you in a few days' time.
現在你們這堛漱u作已經結束了
Now that your work here is finished...
我想你們有很多人會鬆弛下來
...l suppose many of you feel somewhat let down.
這完全可以理解
That's quite understandable.
這是很自然的反應
It's a very natural reaction.
但是某年某月某周某天
But one day, in a week, a month, a year...
在那一天 上帝保佑 我們全部回到自己的家鄉
...on that day when, God willing, we all return to our homes again...
你會對自己在這堛漱u作感到自豪
...you're going to feel very proud of what you've achieved here...
...in the face of great adversity.
你們所做的
What you have done should be...
我想會是
...and I think will be...
我們國民 戰士和市民的榜樣
...an example to all our countrymen, soldier and civilian alike.
你們光榮地生存下來
You have survived with honour.
另外
That, and more.
在這個蠻荒之地
Here in the wilderness...
你們轉敗為勝
...you have turned defeat into victory.
我祝賀你們
I congratulate you.
幹得不錯
Well done.
為了國王
To the king.
你現在就位了
You're in business.
還差什麼嗎？ 樹幹 彈藥 背包 水壺 匕首
Now, you got everything? Stem, ammunition, pack, canteen, knife.
我會直接穿過河流
I'll be directly across the river.
教授說總要以防萬一
The professor says there's always one more thing to do.
但我想不起來要防什麼
I can't think of what it could be.
除了祝你你長命百歲
Except to wish you a long and happy life.
謝謝
Thank you.
發生了什麼事情？
What's happened?
水位降低了
The river's gone down.
可以看到電線了
You can see the wire.
炸藥包！
The charges!
別等火車了
Don't wait for the train.
現在引爆！
Do it now!
如果Saito是對的 火車在5到10分鐘後就會過來
If Saito is correct, the train will arrive in 5 or 1 0 minutes.
如果你不介意 我想從山頂上看
If you don't mind, I'll watch from up on the hill.
為什麼？ 從橋上最好
Why? It's better from the bridge.
很難解釋 先生 我不想成為這典禮的一部分
It's hard to explain, sir. I'd rather not be a part of it.
隨你 說真的 有時我真不瞭解你
As you please. Honestly, sometimes I don't understand you at all.
如你所說 長官 我還要好好學習戰爭
As you once said, sir, I've got a lot to learn about the army.
早上好
Good morning.
夜堣籉鴙飢C了
River's gone down in the night.
他在幹什麼？
What's he doing?
上校 有古怪
Colonel, there's something rather odd going on.
我認為在火車到來之前 我們應該檢查一下
I think we better have a look around before that train comes across.
他簡直瘋了
He's gone mad.
他把他帶到那堨h了！
He's leading him right to it!
可是我們自己人！
Our own man!
我是對的 有古怪
I was right. There is something going on.
幹掉他 孩子！
You've got to do it, boy! You've got to do it now!
你有刀子嗎？ 我認為大橋被下了炸藥了！
Have you a knife? I just realized the bridge has been mined!
炸藥！
Mined!
好小子！
Good boy!
英軍指揮官！ 我來炸掉大橋
British officer! Here to blow up the bridge.
- 炸掉大橋！ - 對 長官 英軍指揮部的命令
- Blow up the bridge! - Yes, sir. British commando orders.
- 炸掉大橋？！ - 是的 沒有時間了！
- Blow up the bridge?! - Yes. There's no time!
不 不行！ 救命！
No, no! Help!
殺掉他！ 殺掉他！
Kill him! Kill him!
讓我走 長官！ 你不明白！
Let me go, sir! You don't understand!
殺掉他！ 殺掉他！
Kill him! Kill him!
殺掉他 喬伊斯！
Kill him, Joyce!
你！
You!
我幹了什麼？
What have I done?
瘋了！
Madness!
我必須這樣做！
I had to do it!
我必須這樣做！ 他們會被活捉的！
I had to do it. They might have been captured alive!
我只能那樣做！
It was the only thing to do!
瘋了！
Madness!